Finding aid for Interlochen Center for The Arts Records, 1927-2005
Bentley Historical Library
- Post-Maddy Administrators, 1958-1995
  - Roger Jacobi, 1971-1989
    - Camp
      The Alphabetical (5) correspondence files, 1988-1989, represent the only portion of the Jacobi papers received in their original order (having been left for his successor Dean Boal). They include correspondence with faculty and staff (past and present), members of the Maddy family, Karl Haas, parents, students, friends, and performers. As Jacobi nears retirement, he often reflects on his experiences at Interlochen and as a young instructor in the Ann Arbor public school system.
      - Administration-Directors
        - Wilson, George
          - 1972-1979, 7 folders (Box 54)
          - 1981-1984-Director Emeritus (Box 54)
        - Downing, Edward J.
          - Selection, 1978 (Box 54)
          - 1979-1989 (Box 54)
        - Directors meetings, minutes, 1987-1989 (Box 54)
      - Admissions, 1980-1989 (Box 54)
      - Anniversary-50th, 1978 (Box 54)
        (see also Box 2: Chrono.-Camp History)
      - Assemblies
        - First, 1981-1989 (Box 54)
        - Final, 1985-1989 (Box 54)
      - Calendar, 1979-1989 (Box 54)
      - Chamber music series (Ardre-Michel Schub), 1983-1985 (Box 54)
      - Choral workshop (proposed)-Ward Swingle, 1985-1986 (Box 54)
      - Enrollment, 1969-1989 (Box 54)
      - Faculty
        - Miller, Frank (early), 1986 (Box 54)
        - Smith, Henry Charles (World Youth Symphony conductor), 1981 (Box 54)
      - Governor's Scholars program, 1987-1988 (Box 54)
      - Jazz workshop
        - Grant application, 1972 (Box 54)
        - Grant application, 1973 (Box 54)
        - Report, 1974 (Box 54)
      - Recording and Broadcast Services Institute, operation and discontinuance (Harold Boxer), 1985-1989; 2 folders (Box 54)
      - Rules and regulations for campers, a review of, 1972-1973 (Box 54)
      - Student government (All Camp Senate), 1986-1989 (Box 54)
      - Suzuki Teachers Workshop, 1979-1984; 2 folders (Box 54)
      - Teaching load reports, 1983-1988 (Box 54)
      - University Division, including All State Agreements with U. of M., 1941; 1970-1985
        - Directors
          - List of, 1941-1982 (Box 54)
          - Correspondence and memos
            - All State
              - Edward J. Downing, 1973-1975 (Box 54)
              - Donald Sinta, 1984-1985 (Box 54)
            - University
              - Boylan, Paul, 1971-1975; 2 folders (Box 54)
              - McCollum, John, 1976-1977 (Box 54)
              - Hurst, Lawrence, 1977-1982 (Box 54)
          - Reports (University and All State), 1971-1983; 4 folders (Box 55)
    - Alphabetical correspondence files
      - (including Clare Burns (Treasurer), September 1988-August 1989; 25 folders (Box 55)
      - Including Clare Burns (Treasurer), September-December 1989; 23 folders (Box 56)
  - Boal, 1989-1995
    Boal contains his correspondence files plus subject files which he considered unneeded for reference by his successor. The correspondence focuses on the administration of Interlochen, including the name change for the Camp and the successful fund-raising necessitated by a cut in state aid. His interchanges with Jacobi show his view of developments at Interlochen, and his correspondence with alumni leader, Gerilyn Turner, reveal the tensions inherent in attempts at institutional change. The subject files emphasize developments at Interlochen's three major units: the radio station (WIAA), the Academy, and the Camp.
    - Alphabetical correspondence files
      - 1989-1992, 52 folders (Box 66)
      - 1992-1995, 72 folders (Box 85)
    - Subject files
      - Biographical (Box 85)
      - Interlochen
        - Broadcasting (WIAA)
          - Administration
            - Director (Thom Paulson), 1990-1991 (Box 85)
          - Financial/fund raising
            - Corporation for Public Broadcasting, grants/reports, 1990-1991 (Box 85)
            - General, 1990-1991 (Box 85)
          - Listener survey, 1991 (Box 85)
          - Recording services, 1990-1992 (Box 85)
        - Publicity/promotion
          - Community and Public Relations Department, objectives and goals, 1992 (Box 85)
        - Strategic planning for the nineties, 1990-1993; 2 folders (Box 85)
      - Academy
        - Accreditation (U. of M. report), 1990-1992 (Box 85)
        - Admissions, 1992-1993 (Box 85)
        - Assemblies (Recognition-student awards), 1992-1994 (Box 85)
        - Commencement, 1990-1993; 4 folders (Box 86)
        - Divisions
          - Art (Visual), 1990 (Box 86)
          - Dance, 1991-1993 (Box 86)
          - Drama/Theatre, 1990-1993 (Box 86)
          - Literary Arts, 1990 (Box 86)
          - Math/Science, 1990-1992 (Box 86)
          - Music, 1990-1993 (Box 86)
        - Library, 1990-1992 (Box 86)
        - Special Events
          - Orchestra, Mozart Tour, 1990-1992 (Box 86)
          - Piano Festival, 1990-1991 (Box 86)
      - Camp
        - Administration
          - Plans for name change, 1990 (Box 86)
          - Boal address to donors, 1991 (Box 86)
          - Director (Ed Downing), 1990-1991 (Box 86)
          - Camp (Division) directors, 1990-1991 (Box 86)
          - Staff, pre-Camp meeting, 1992 (Box 86)
          - Admissions study, 1988-1992 (Box 86)
        - Assemblies
          - First, 1990-1991 (Box 86)
          - Final (Awards), 1990-1992 (Box 86)
        - Calendar, 1990-1991 (Box 86)
        - Enrollment, 1990-1993 (Box 86)
        - Reports-Theatre Arts Division, 1990; 1991; 2 folders (Box 86)
        - Student government-All Camp Senate, 1990 (Box 86)
        - Surveys of Campers and potential Campers, 1990-1991 (Box 86)
        - University Division-All State operations, 1990 (Box 86)
  - Szady
    Szady documents her role, 1992-1995, as an alumna in campus planning/fund raising and on the board of the Interlochen Alumni Organization. A small file of informational materials covers the transition from the Boal to the Odell administration.
    - Interlochen
      - Alumni Organization
        - Correspondence, 1992-1995 (Box 86)
        - Bylaw revision, 1992-1993 (Box 86)
        - Membership, lists and biographies, 1992-1995 (Box 86)
        - Agendas, 1992-1995 (Box 86)
        - Minutes and reports, 1992-1995 (Box 86)
        - Lists of prominent alumni, 1993; 1994 (Box 86)
      - Committees
        - General
          - Membership lists, 1992-1995 (Box 86)
          - Agendas, 1992-1995 (Box 86)
          - Miscellaneous, 1993 (Box 86)
        - Specific
          - Advancement, papers, 1992-1995 (Box 86)
          - Finance, reports, 1993-1995 (Box 86)
          - Student Life and Special Projects, minutes and reports (including photo archives), 1992-1995 (Box 86)
    - Miscellaneous (fund-raising, building, etc.)
      - Campus Master Plan (Sasaki Associates), 1991 (Box 86)
      - Building Committee, Wellness/Campus Center, 1993 (Box 86)
      - Printed and ephemera
        - Fund raising, 1992-1996 (Box 86)
        - Articles re. Interlochen, 1993-1995 (Box 86)
      - Presidential transition materials, 1994-1995 (Box 86)
  - Odell, 1995-1997
    Odell is composed of alphabetical correspondence files spanning the years from1995-1997.
    - Alphabetical correspondence files
      - A-S, 1995-1996; 20 folders (Box 86)
      - S-Z, 1995-1996; 4 folders (Box 86)
      - A-Z, 1996-1997; 24 folders (Box 67)
  - Downing, 1998-2000
    Downing contains but three folders of correspondence organized chronologically and spanning the period from 1998-2000.
    - Chronological correspondence
      - 1998-2000, 3 folders (Box 67)
- Boards, 1928-89
  The Boards series covers Interlochen's support and governing bodies: Board of Advisors, Board of Control, and Board of Directors/Trustees. Advisory served in a consulting and fund-raising capacity from the Camp's founding until the early 1970's while Control oversaw its financial operations through the payment of early creditors in 1943. The Board of Directors, whose name was officially changed to Trustees in 1944, constituted the official governing body throughout Interlochen's history.
  The Board of Advisors dates to the Camp's founding and continued through World War II. In 1960, as Maddy was planning the Academy, he revived it, and in 1965, expanded it to cover all operations. During the early 1970's, as the Board of Trustees membership was significantly increased, it apparently became moribund. While operating, it provided counsel, recruited students, and in particular, aided fund-raising. In the 1960's, Karl Haas served as its head before becoming president of Interlochen.
  - Advisory Board, 1940-1945; 1960-1971
    The advisory board records consist mainly of correspondence for 1940-1945 and 1960-1969. Maddy and board co-chairs, Peter Dykema and Mrs. R. B. Canfield, dominate the early period, and Maddy, Merrill, and Haas the later. While much of the material relates to meeting arrangements, some elaborates on Interlochen developments as well as personal subjects.
    Letters of advisory board members dealing with non-board business can also be found in the Special Correspondence of the Chronological series. In addition, the Board of Trustees subseries contains correspondence from some former advisory board members (especially from the 1960's). Since fund-raising constituted a major focus of the advisory board throughout its history. researchers should also consult that topic in the Subject Interlochen and Post-Maddy Administrators Haas series.
    - Early, correspondence and minutes, 1940-1945; 9 folders (Box 56)
    - General letters and membership lists, 1960-1971
      - Gillis/Maddy, 1960-1964 (Box 56)
      - Maddy/Merrill, 1965-1967 (Box 56)
      - Haas, 1967-1969 (Box 56)
      - Membership list, 1971 (Box 56)
    - Alpha correspondence files, 1964-1969
      - Beers, Julius, 1965-1969 (Box 56)
      - Bowman, Jon G., 1965-1969 (Box 56)
      - Boxer, Harold, 1965-1969 (Box 56)
      - Brown, Grant H., 1965-1969 (Box 56)
      - Cross, Richard E., 1964-1968 (Box 56)
      - Czukor, Eugene J. and Barbara Britton, 1967-1969 (Box 56)
      - Dello Joio, Norman, 1965-1967 (Box 56)
      - Dow, Alden B., 1965-1969 (Box 56)
      - Downs, Hugh, 1965-1967 (Box 56)
      - Fink, Mrs. Lou Kent, 1967-1969 (Box 56)
      - Fischer, Gerald J., 1966-1970 (Box 56)
      - Goldenson, Leonard H., 1965-1967 (Box 56)
      - Gonzales, Donald J., 1965-1970; 2 folders (Box 56)
      - Griffin, Robert P., 1965-1969 (Box 56)
      - Haas, Karl, 1965-1967 (Box 56)
      - Hoey, Harry D., 1965-1966 (Box 56)
      - Honigman, Mrs. Maurice (Nat'l Fed. of Women's Clubs), 1967 (Box 56)
      - Huey, Arthur S., 1965-1969 (Box 56)
      - Kresge, Stanley S., 1964-1967 (Box 56)
      - Klein, David E., 1967-1968 (Box 56)
      - Lawler, Vanett (MENC), 1965-1967 (Box 56)
      - McGuire, Whitney S., 1964-1969 (Box 56)
      - McWhorter, Charles K., 1965-1969 (Box 56)
      - Megee, 1965-1968 (Box 56)
      - Mott, C.S. Harding, 1965-1967 (Box 56)
      - Muir, Mrs. Clifton (Nat'l Fed. of Music Clubs), 1964-1967 (Box 56)
      - Nagelvoort, Bernard A., 1967-1969 (Box 56)
      - Neuman, Herman, 1965-1968 (Box 56)
      - Ogg, Norma Lee Browning, 1966-1969 (Box 56)
      - Parkman, Francis, Jr., 1965-1967 (Box 56)
      - Parsons, Mrs. John T., 1965-1969 (Box 56)
      - Pelletier, Wilfred and Brampton, Rose, 1965-1968 (Box 56)
      - Power, Eugene, 1965-1968 (Box 56)
      - Radock, Michael, 1966-1969 (Box 56)
      - Rector, Gail, 1965-1969 (Box 56)
      - Rolfing, R.C., 1965-1967 (Box 56)
      - Roller, A. Clyde, 1965-1969 (Box 56)
      - Romney, Mrs. George, 1965-1969 (Box 56)
      - Rosenbaum, Samuel R., 1965-1969 (Box 56)
      - Stirton, William E., 1965-1968 (Box 56)
      - Swaney, Russel A., 1965-1968 (Box 56)
      - Tanis, Preston, 1965-1968 (Box 56)
      - Taylor, Deems, 1965-1966 (Box 56)
      - Ten Hoor, Martin, 1965-1967 (Box 56)
      - Toscanini, Walter, 1964-1967 (Box 56)
      - Van Bodegraven, Paul, 1965-1966 (Box 56)
      - Wilhousky, Peter J., 1965-1969 (Box 56)
      - Wogan, Robert, 1965-1967 (Box 56)
  - Board of Control, 1928-1942
    While the Board of Advisors provided support, the Board of Control oversaw the Camp's financial operations from 1928 until 1943. It represented the interests of the early creditors, especially the debenture holders, a large proportion of whom came from the Traverse City area. Willis Pennington, from whom the Camp property was purchased, played a major role in its deliberations. When the initial debt was retired in 1943, the Board of Control ceased to exist.
    Its few surviving records, 1928-1942, consist of correspondence, papers, and reports of a financial nature. They include the contractual arrangements for the first Camp broadcasts, 1930. Researchers will also want to consult: the Pennington family materials in Chronological Camp History, the Tremaine correspondence in Chronological Camp files, and the debenture files in Subject Interlochen -"Fund raising."
    - Early financial history by C.M. Tremaine, 1956 (Box 56)
    - Papers, 1928-1942 (Box 56)
  - Board of Trustees (Directors until 1944), 1928-1989
    The Board of Directors/Trustees served as Interlochen's official governing body from its beginning. Rather than being incorporated by the state legislature, Maddy, Giddings, and Pennington formed an association with themselves as members. The members and board were synonymous, but to satisfy legal requirements, the former met annually in advance of the board to add or delete from their number and hear reports. The board session which followed made the policy decisions. Members serving in their capacity on the Board were called Directors until 1944, when the Camp formally altered its name and bylaws, making them Trustees.
    As long as Maddy was president, the Board remained relatively small, and much business, particularly in the early years, was conducted on an informal basis. In 1930, Tremaine replaced Pennington on the three person Board, and a year later, Howard Hanson was added. During the late 1930's and early 1940's, it expanded to seven members with the inclusion of Franklin Dunham (1938), Judith Waller (1941), and J. Joseph Herbert (1942), the latter representing the University of Michigan. In 1943, W. W. Charters replaced Hanson. When first Giddings and then Tremaine became less active, Maddy was able to shape the board more to his liking. Although newcomers were added, it remained less than a dozen members until Maddy's death.
    Following Maddy's passing, the Board underwent a rapid expansion. At Haas' resignation in 1970, it had twenty-two members, and at Jacobi's retirement in 1989, forty-one. As the board grew, much of its work was done by committees. The first, an executive committee, was formed, apparently in the late 1940's, to act in the Board's behalf between meetings. Under Maddy's successors, the number of committees handling specific subjects proliferated.
    The Trustee/Director records are by far the most extensive and complete of the three Interlochen Boards. They are divided into two sections:(1) correspondence and papers, 1928-1988, and (2) minutes and reports, 1930-89. The former includes some supporting documents, and the latter many reports used in decision making.
    - Correspondence and papers
      The "correspondence and papers" (1), 1928-1988, is divided chronologically into files for (a) Maddy, 1928-1966, (b) the Administrative Committee, 1966-1967, Haas, 1967-1970, (d) acting president Wilson, 1970-71, and (e) Jacobi, 1971-88. The correspondence consists of exchanges between the Trustees and Interlochen officers, especially the president, president's secretary, treasurer, and board secretary. Everything directly relates to board business. Correspondence of a private nature or about Interlochen in general usually can be found elsewhere.
      The Maddy segment (a), 1928-1966, is organized chronologically except for a concluding alphabetical file for significant Trustees, 1959-1966. The latter includes Roscoe Bonisteel, who became chairman of the board after Maddy's death, and Clement Stone, the philanthropist who endowed the Academy. Other than an occasional letter from Maddy's secretary (Stace) or the Camp treasurer (largely Tremaine), Maddy handled almost all the surviving early Trustee correspondence. Additional communications from Trustees can be found under Giddings and Tremaine in the Chronological Camp files, 1935-1966, and especially under Dunham and Waller in Special Correspondence. With the appointment of Board secretaries Roger Jacobi, 1956-1959, and John Merrill, 1959-1969, correspondence with trustees increased markedly. Merrill was especially active in maintaining contact with them.
      The Administrative Committee portion, 1966-1967, (b) provides much of the surviving documentation on the operation of Interlochen immediately after Maddy's death, including the selection of his successor. It also helps illuminate the fund-raising efforts of the era. Merrill, as committee secretary, and Stace, as a committee member and Maddy's long-time aide, dominate the Trustee correspondence.
      Haas' files, 1967-1970, largely reflect his personal dealings with the board but also include letters from Merrill and Stace. During the Haas presidency, six new trustees were appointed, and the President of the Interlochen Alumni Association (David E. Klein until 1970) became an ex officio member. Two of the seven new trustees, Klein and Eugene Power, previously served with Haas on the Advisory Board.
      Files for the Wilson acting presidency (d), 1970-1971, contain some of the best information available on the administration of Interlochen between Haas' resignation and Jacobi's appointment. They include materials on the reaction to the resignation, particularly at the Academy, and the presidential selection process.
      The Jacobi files (e), 1971-1988, are alphabetically organized, reflecting the expansion of the board under his presidency. Correspondence from his first few months in office is lacking, and the files of many important board members end currently in 1984, including with Clement Stone. The latter became chairman upon Roscoe Bonisteel's death in 1972 and played an important role throughout the Jacobi presidency. Jacobi handled almost all the correspondence himself. In a letter to Stone of September 22, 1980, he elaborates on his achievements as president.
      - Yearly summary of changes in appointments, 1928-1979 (Box 57)
      - Maddy era, 1928-1966
        - Chronological
          - General papers, 1928-1939 (Box 57)
          - Traverse City bank loans, 1932-1942; 1945 (Box 57)
          - Commission proposal, 1939 (Box 57)
          - General papers, 1940-1943 (Box 57)
          - Incorporation amendments, 1943-1944 (Box 57)
          - General papers, 1944-1966; 12 folders (Box 57)
        - Alphabetical
          - Attwood, Charles, 1959-1964 (Box 57)
          - Bonisteel, Roscoe O., Sr., 1958-1966 (Box 57)
          - Cliburn, Van, 1964-1966 (Box 57)
          - Dow, Herbert H., 1964-1966 (Box 57)
          - Dunham, Franklin, 1959-1964 (Box 57)
          - Gordon, Britton, 1960-1966 (Box 57)
          - Hanson, Howard, 1956-1966 (Box 57)
          - Knuth, William E., 1956-1966 (Box 57)
          - Marvel, David T., 1965-1967 (Box 57)
          - Ormandy, Eugene, 1965-1966 (Box 57)
          - Stone, W. Clement
            - Maddy
              - General, 1961-1966; 6 folders (Box 57)
              - Gift of Maori carvings, 1962-1963 (Box 57)
              - Press releases on gift to Academy, 1964 (Box 57)
            - Merrill, 1963-1966 (Box 57)
            - Stace, 1964-1965 (Box 57)
      - Administrative Committee, 1966-1967
        - Chronological
          - Ad Hoc/Executive Committee, 1966-1967 (Box 57)
          - General (Merrill), 1966-1967 (Box 57)
          - Presidential candidates, 1966 (Box 57)
          - News releases, presidential selection, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Alphabetical
          - Belcher, Donald R. (Box 57)
          - Bonisteel, Roscoe (Box 57)
          - Cliburn, Van (Box 57)
          - Dow, Herbert (Box 57)
          - Gordon, Britton (Box 57)
          - Hanson, Howard (Box 57)
          - Knuth, William (Box 57)
          - Maddy, Mrs. Joseph E. (Box 57)
          - Marvel, David (Box 57)
          - Ormandy, Eugene (Box 57)
          - Stone, Clement
            - Merrill correspondence (Box 57)
            - Stace correspondence (Box 57)
      - Haas, 1967-1970
        - Chronological, general (Box 57)
        - Alphabetical
          - Adams, Charles F. (new 1968) (Box 58)
          - Belcher, Donald R. (Box 58)
          - Bonisteel, Roscoe O. (Box 58)
          - Brittain, W.L. (new 1969) (Box 58)
          - Cliburn, Van (Box 58)
          - Dow, Herbert H. (executive committee) (Box 58)
          - Frohlich, Edward P. (new 1968) (Box 58)
          - Gordon, Britton L. (exec. com.) (Box 58)
          - Hanson, Howard (Box 58)
          - Jones, Ernest A. (new 1970) (Box 58)
          - Klein, David E. (new 1968) (Box 58)
          - Knuth, William E. (Box 58)
          - Maddy, Fay (Box 58)
          - Marvel, David T. (Box 58)
          - Ormandy, Eugene (Box 58)
          - Patterson, W. Calvin (new 1968) (Box 58)
          - Power, Eugene B. (new 1968) (Box 58)
          - Stone, W. Clement (Box 58)
          - Vroman, Clyde (exec. com.) (Box 58)
          - Wallace, James B. (exec. com.) (Box 58)
          - Warner, Harold G. (new 1968) (Box 58)
      - Wilson, 1970-1971
        - Subject
          - Academy reaction to Haas resignation (Box 58)
          - Presidential search committee (Box 58)
          - Wilson administrative (Box 58)
          - Ad Hoc Committee (Box 58)
        - Alphabetical (largely Stace)
          - Bonisteel, Roscoe O. (Box 58)
          - Cliburn, Van (Box 58)
          - Maddy, Fay (Box 58)
          - Stone, W. Clement (Box 58)
      - Jacobi, 1971-1988
        - Bass, Robert H., 1981-1985 (Box 58)
        - Brandel, Paul W., 1978-1988 (Box 58)
        - Britton, Allen P., 1973-1984; 2 folders (Box 58)
        - Ceccato, Eliana (Mrs. Aldo), 1974-1977 (Box 58)
        - Cliburn, Van, 1973-1984 (Box 58)
        - Currie, Donald H., 1972-1985 (Box 58)
        - Dendrinos, Peter C., 1968; 1976-1984 (Box 58)
        - Dexter, Elaine (Mrs. Louis), 1975-1984 (Box 58)
        - Dow, Barbara (Mrs. Herbert), 1984 (Box 58)
        - Easlick, David K., 1982-1984 (Box 58)
        - Edwards, Esther G., 1984 (Box 58)
        - Ellis, Charles C., 1982-1984 (Box 58)
        - Fischer, Gerald J., 1979-1988 (Box 58)
        - Ford, Cristina (Mrs. Henry II), 1974-1980 (Box 58)
        - Frolich, Edward P., 1972-1984 (Box 58)
        - Gonzales, Donald J., 1974-1984 (Box 58)
        - Gordon, Britton L., 1972-1988; 2 folders (Box 58)
        - Handleman, David, 1978-1984 (Box 58)
        - Hanson, Howard (Emeritus), 1972-1981 (Box 58)
        - Hayden, Martin S., 1978-1983 (Box 58)
        - Jones, Ernest A., 1972-1984 (Box 58)
        - Keith, Damon J., 1972-1984 (Box 58)
        - Knuth, William E. (Emeritus), 1988 (Box 58)
        - Luney, William E., 1982-1984 (Box 58)
        - Maddy, Fay (Emeritus), 1973-1985 (Box 58)
        - Marvel, David T., 1976-1988 (Box 58)
        - McCarthy, Walter J., Jr., 1981-1988 (Box 58)
        - McHenry, Barnabas, 1984-1986 (Box 58)
        - McWhorter, Charles K., 1972-1984; 2 folders (Box 58)
        - Milliken, William G., 1980-1984 (Box 58)
        - Muer, Charles A., 1977-1983 (Box 58)
        - Osterlin, Helen, 1976; 1980; 1983; 1984 (Box 58)
        - Patterson, W. Calvin, 1982-1986 (Box 58)
        - Richardson, Dean E., 1975-1984 (Box 59)
        - Roe, Charlotte (Mrs. J. Woodward), 1973-1984 (Box 59)
        - Schwartz, Alan E., 1973-1977; 1983 (Box 59)